Guide to the COYOTE Rhode Island records 1990-2019
Brown University Library
COYOTE Rhode Island records
1990-2019
Ms.2019.019
John Hay Library University Archives and Manuscripts Box A Brown University Providence, RI, 02912 Telephone: Manuscripts: 401-863-3723; University Archives: 401-863-2148 Email: Manuscripts: hay@brown.edu; University Archives: archives@brown.edu
2.5 linear feet (1 record center carton, 2 file boxes, 2 half file boxes, and 1 oversize folder)
Bella Robinson; COYOTE Rhode Island
This collection contains the organizational records of COYOTE Rhode Island, a group of sex workers, former sex workers, trafficking victims, and allies, who advocate for policies that promote the health and safety of people involved in the sex industry. Materials include administrative records; special project files such as the COYOTE-RI Impact Survey and Sex Workers Outreach Project pen pal letters; subject files regarding other advocacy organizations; public records of court cases, arrests, and legislation relating to prostitution; and informational zines and booklets. The collections dates from 1990 to 2019.
Biographical/Historical Note
Call Off Your Old Tired Ethics (COYOTE) is a national grassroots social justice network founded by Margo St. James in San Francisco, California, in 1973. It is dedicated to the fundamental human rights of sex workers and their communities. COYOTE focuses on ending violence and stigma through education, community building, and advocacy. COYOTE looks to improve the lives of sex workers, end the criminalization of sex work, and erase the stigma associated with sex work. COYOTE Rhode Island was founded by Bella Robinson in 2009 and is the only state chapter of this nationwide organization.
COYOTE-RI stands in solidarity with many social justice movements including Black Lives Matter, disability rights, criminal justice reform, the undocumented, the homeless, gender equality and the LGBTQ movement, and the rights of the working class. COYOT-RI recognizes that many people choose to do sex work due to limited options in other sectors, often due to marginalization and discrimination along the lines of race, gender, ability, sexuality, and immigration status, and that those who do choose to engage with the sex industry should not be further criminalized. As an organization, COYOT-RI has existed to support sex workers in crisis, serve as an advocate for sex workers in the political sector, and provide education on the reality of sex workers and how best to be an ally to sex workers in the New England area.
Bella Robinson is a sex worker’s rights activist who has worked in the sex industry for over thirty years. As the director of COYOT-RI, Robinson looks to build and strengthen support networks for sex workers in Rhode Island and she works in close collaboration with activists nationwide. She is a strong proponent of centering the voices of sex workers in policies that affect their population. In the late 90’s she was incarcerated for five years at Lowell Correctional Institute in Florida, and during incarceration experienced sexual assault at the hands of the state. It is with this perspective that she advocates for sex worker rights as a solution to policies that seek carceral redress for sex trafficking crimes.
From 2012 to 2018, Robinson also served as a board member and secretary of The Erotic Service Providers Union Legal, Education and Research Project (ESPLERP), a diverse community-based erotic service provider-led group that seeks to empower the erotic community and advances sexual privacy rights through legal advocacy, education, and research. Additionally, Robinson is on the advisory committee of the Sex Worker Outreach Project Behind Bars (SWOP Behind Bars), an organization that supports incarcerated sex workers. With SWOP Behind bars, Robinson works to send over 1,000 incarcerated sex workers a newsletter every month. Incarcerated sex workers are also supported through pen pal programs, a book program and 6 paralegal correspondence courses every year. SWOP Behind Bars and COYOTE also act as case managers to help those being released to access reentry services.
In 2013, Robinson was featured in the award-winning film “American Courtesans” as Gina Robinson. In 2014, Robinson began a collaboration with Elena Shih, Assistant Professor of American and Ethnic Studies and a fellow at the Center for the Study of Slavery and Justice, human trafficking research cluster, at Brown University. Together Robinson and Shih host speakers, events, and course lectures, which look at justice for the poor, issues of the carceral state, understanding and critiquing human trafficking, harm reduction, and sex work as a profession. In 2017, COYOT-RI developed the Impact Survey with assistance from Shih and the Center for the Study of Slavery and Justice at Brown University. The survey asked sex workers who advertised their services on Back Page 145 questions about the impact of anti-trafficking legislation on their lives and work. The digital survey responses are available for research in the Special Collections Reading Room of the John Hay Library.
Robinson plans to continue donating her personal papers to the Pembroke Center Archives at Brown University in the future. She currently resides in Rhode Island and has one daughter.
Collection information
This collection contains the organizational records of COYOTE Rhode Island, a group of sex workers, former sex workers, trafficking victims, and allies, who advocate for policies that promote the health and safety of people involved in the sex industry. Materials include administrative records; special project files such as the COYOTE-RI Impact Survey and Sex Workers Outreach Project pen pal letters; subject files regarding other advocacy organizations; public records of court cases, arrests, and legislation relating to prostitution; and informational zines and booklets. The collections dates from 1990 to 2019 and is arranged into 7 series.
Series 1, ADMINISTRATIVE, 2013-2019, includes articles, correspondence, and informational materials related to the mission and advocacy work of COYOT-RI. Particularly interesting materials include an article on Bella Robinson’s advocacy work and a letter to the editor by Robinson regarding myths about the sex industry. This series is arranged alphabetically by record type.
Series 2, SPECIAL PROJECTS, 2012-2019, contains planning and outreach files related to special projects conducted by COYOT-RI and collaborations between COYOT-RI and outside entities, specifically Brown University and the Sex Workers Outreach Project.
In approximately 2014, Bella Robinson began visiting the Brown campus, speaking about COYOT-RI at the Sarah Doyle Center, co-hosting advocacy events, and lecturing in classes taught by Assistant Professor of American and Ethnic Studies Elena Shih. Topics included justice for the poor, issues of the carceral state, understanding and critiquing human trafficking, harm reduction, and sex work as a profession. In 2017, COYOT-RI developed the Impact Survey with assistance from the Center for the Study of Slavery and Justice at Brown University. The survey asked sex workers who advertised their services on Back Page 145 questions about the impact on their lives of the passing of the United States House bill known as FOSTA, the Fight Online Sex Trafficking Act, and the Senate bill, SESTA, the Stop Enabling Sex Traffickers Act. To date, 1,515 sex workers have responded, providing long form responses. Administrative files related to this survey and response data is available as part of this collection. Survey responses are digital and available for research in the Special Collections Reading Room of the John Hay Library.
The Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars supports incarcerated sex workers through a monthly newsletter, pen pal program, book program, and paralegal correspondence courses. Files in this series contain letters between Robinson and incarcerated sex workers and touch upon the sex industry, life in prison, and expectations of life upon release. The correspondence has been redacted to protect the identity of incarcerated people and original letters closed. Redacted use copies are arranged alphabetically by correspondent’s first and last initials and are open for research.
Series 2 is arranged alphabetically by organization and then by record type.
Series 3, EVENTS, 2013-2019, includes pamphlets, flyers, and schedules related to events hosted by COYOT-RI or attended by Robinson. Events include The Sex Worker Rights Movement: Addressing Justice Conference, International Day to End Violence Against Sex Workers, and the Women’s March in Providence, Rhode Island. This series is arranged alphabetically by event name.
Series 4, OTHER ADVOCACY ORGANIZATIONS, 2010-2018, includes booklets, calendars, flyers, and news articles related to organizations that also advocate for sex worker rights and safety. Organizations include Butterfly: Asian and Migrant Sex Workers Support Network, International Sex Worker Foundation for Art, Culture, and Education, and United States Prostitutes Collective. This series is arranged alphabetically by name of the organization.
Series 5, PUBLIC RECORDS AND RELATED RESEARCH, 2009-2019, includes legislative House Bills, Acts, and Resolutions; arrest reports, and news articles concerning decriminalization of prostitution in Rhode Island and New Hampshire. Of particular note are the written testimonies in support of Rhode Island House Bill 5354 to create a special legislative commission to study the health and safety impact of revising commercial sexual activity laws. This series is arranged alphabetically by record type.
Series 6, PRINT MATERIAL, 1990-2019, contains magazine, newsletters, note cards and post cards, and zines. Titles include “Assata’s Testimony, 1973,” “Ladies of the Evening: The Improv 10/27/98,” “Prostitutes of New York Press: a newsletter published by and for the New York City sex workers’ community.” This series is arranged alphabetically by title.
Series 7, RESTRICTED, 2002-2019, is arranged into 2 subseries.
Series 7, subseries 1, BELLA ROBINSON’S PERSONAL PAPERS, 2002-2018 includes awards, clippings, and photos. Additional materials will be added to this subseries. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by record type and is restricted for 25 years until January 1, 2044, after which date it will open without restriction.
SERIES 7, subseries 2, GENERAL RESTRICTED FILES, contains the original un-redacted copies of correspondence to and from Bella Robinson through the Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent’s first and last initials and is closed for 50 years, until January 1, 2069, after which date it will open without restriction.
There are no restrictions on access, except SERIES 7, Bella Robinson’s personal papers, is restricted for 25 years until January 1, 2044, and SERIES 8, Restricted, is closed for 50 years, until January 1, 2069. The collection can only be seen by prior appointment. Some materials may be stored off-site and cannot be produced on the same day on which they are requested.
This collection is arranged into 7 series.
Series 1. Administrative
Series 2. Special Projects
Series 3. Events
Series 4. Other Advocacy Organizations
Series 5. Public Records and Related Research
Series 6. Print Material
Series 7. Restricted
Subseries 1. Bella Robinson's personal papers
Subseries 2. General Restricted Files
Administrative information
Gift of Bella Robinson beginning in 2018.
Additional information
See also the COYOTE-RI Survey Collection partially available through Brown University’s Digital Repository: https://repository.library.brown.edu/studio/collections/id_938/; and the Records of COYOTE, 1962-1989 (81-M32--90-M1), at Harvard University’s Schlesinger Library. View finding aid here: https://hollisarchives.lib.harvard.edu/repositories/8/resources/5083
- Administrative, 2013 - 2019; Series 1
  - Article re: COYOTE Rhode Island and Bella Robinson's advocacy for sex workers, circa 2015 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from Bella Robinson to the Center for Sex and Culture, San Francisco, 2019 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re: thank you notes, 2019 (Box 1)
  - Ephemera: buttons, bookmark, stickers, and zine (Box 1)
  - Fact sheets, information cards, and pamphlets, circa 2018 (Box 1)
  - Internship supervisor statement, 2017 (Box 1)
  - Letter to the editor by Bella Robinson re: myths about sex industry, 2016 (Box 1)
  - Mission and description of COYOTE Rhode Island (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 2016 - 2019 (Box 1)
- Special Projects, 2012 - 2019; Series 2
  - Brown University collaboration with Professor Elena Shih; course syllabus and article by Shih, "The High Price of Freedom: Moral Economies of Low-Wage Women's Work in the Transnational Anti-Human Trafficking Movement", 2014 (Box 1)
  - COYOTE-RI Impact survey: correspondence, 2016 (Box 1)
    Original survey data available for research in the Special Collections Reading Room, John Hay Library
  - COYOTE-RI Impact survey: information sheets and court document, 2017 - 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project: website homepage printout and news articles, 2012 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: booklets, flyers, and pamphlets, circa 2017 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to A. C. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to A. M. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to C. D. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to C. D. B. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to J. L. B. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to J. P. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to K. M. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to L. F. W. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to L. P. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to L. T. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to M. O. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to M. S. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to N. P. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to R. J. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence to T. E. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with A. C. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with A. C. [redacted use copy], 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with A. M. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with A. W. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with B. T. [redacted use copy], 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with C. B. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with D. S. [redacted use copy], 2018 - 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with H. K. T. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with H. K. W. [redacted use copy], 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with J. F. [redacted use copy], 2018 - 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with J. F. [redacted use copy], 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with J. H. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with J. M. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with J. N. [redacted use copy], 2018 - 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with K. S. [redacted use copy], 2018 - 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with L. G. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with L. H. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with M. B. [redacted use copy], 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with M. H. [redacted use copy], 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with M. S. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with M. S. [redacted use copy], 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with P. J. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with P. M. R. (1 of 2) [redacted use copy], 2017 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with P. M. R. (2 of 2) [redacted use copy], 2018 - 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with R. W. [redacted use copy], 2018 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with S. B. [redacted use copy], 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with S. D. [redacted use copy], 2018 - 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex Workers Outreach Project Behind Bars: correspondence with T. W. [redacted use copy], 2017 - 2018 (Box 1)
- Events, 2013 - 2019; Series 3
  - Boston Labor Conference: schedule pamphlet, 2017 (Box 1)
  - Day One: Sexual Violence Ends Here Conference: evaluation and registration email, 2015 (Box 1)
  - Desiree Alliance: The Audacity of Health: Sex Work, Health and Politics Conference: booklet, 2013 (Box 1)
  - Desiree Alliance: The Sex Worker Rights Movement: Addressing Justice Conference: reading and correspondence to Bella Robinson, 2016 (Box 1)
  - End Rhode Island Trafficking Conference: packet of American Civil Liberties Union materials, 2015 (Box 1)
  - International Day to End Violence Against Sex Workers: flyer, 2019 (Box 1)
  - International Day to End Violence Against Sex Workers; includes press release, flyers, and news articles, 2017 (Box 1)
  - International Day to End Violence Against Sex Workers: invitation from COYOTE Rhode Island, 2018 (Box 1)
  - International Sex Workers Day; includes posters, presentation materials, and Bella Robinson's speech, circa 2016 (Box 1)
  - International Transgender Day of Remembrance; includes agenda and list of names, 2015 (Box 1)
  - LEAD Community Call; includes invitee list and meeting notes (Box 1)
  - Naming (In)Justice: Rights and Resistance Across Queer Migrations and Trafficking Symposium and Zine Workshop: booklet, 2018 (Box 1)
  - New Orleans Harm Reduction Conference: zine and booklet (Box 1)
  - Northeast Regional Conference: ticket, 2019 (Box 1)
  - Sex and Migration Panel Discussion: outline, 2019 (Box 1)
  - Summer School for Union Women; includes schedule, workshop descriptions, and songbook, 2015 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified conference: schedule, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Various events: oversize posters, circa 2011 (Box Pembroke Center Archives catch-all oversize box 3XXX)
  - Whitewashing Abolition: Race, Displacement, and Combating Human Trafficking Conference: booklet, description, and schedule, 2018 (Box 1)
  - Women's March, Providence, Rhode Island; includes promotional materials, tickets, and Bella Robinson's speech, 2018 (Box 1)
- Other Advocacy Organizations, 2010 - 2018; Series 4
  - Butterfly: Asian and Migrant Sex Workers Support Network: informational booklets and flyers, 2017 (Box 1)
  - Caribbean Vulnerable Communities Coalition: pamphlet, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Community United for Safety and Protection: Advocating Safety and Protection for all People in Alaska's Sex Trade: pamphlet and printout, circa 2012 (Box 1)
  - Erotic Service Providers Union; includes flyers, pamphlets, and talking points (Box 1)
  - International Sex Worker Foundation for Art, Culture, and Education: booklets and flyers, 2013 - 2015 (Box 1)
  - International Sex Worker Foundation for Art, Culture, and Education: calendar, 2011 (Box 1)
  - International Sex Worker Foundation for Art, Culture, and Education: calendar, 2015 (Box 1)
  - International Sex Worker Foundation for Art, Culture, and Education: calendar, 2016 (Box 1)
  - International Sex Worker Foundation for Art, Culture, and Education: news articles, 2015 - 2016 (Box 1)
  - International Sex Worker Foundation for Art, Culture, and Education: statistical booklet, 2018 (Box 1)
  - International Sex Worker Foundation for Art, Culture, and Education: website printout re: mission, projects, and overview, 2012 (Box 1)
  - New Jersey Red Umbrella Alliance: flyers, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Rhode Island Commission for Human Rights: annual report, 2017 (Box 1)
  - Saint James Infirmary: Occupational Health and Safety Handbook (1 of 2), 2010 (Box 1)
  - Saint James Infirmary: Occupational Health and Safety Handbook (2 of 2), 2010 (Box 1)
  - Sex Work Activists, Allies, and You: website printout and news articles, 2012 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified organization: "responses to guest speakers and the film 'American Courtesans'", 2013 (Box 1)
  - United States Prostitutes Collective: handouts (Box 1)
  - Various organizations: promotional cards for documentaries re: sex workers, n.d. (Box 1)
- Public Records and Related Research, 2009 - 2019; Series 5
  - An Act Relating to Criminal Offenses - Prostitution and Lewdness (Rhode Island), 2018 (Box 2)
  - An Act Relating to Criminal Offenses - Sexual Assault (Rhode Island); includes speech transcript and news release, 2019 (Box 2)
  - An Act Relating to Criminal Offenses for Commercial Sexual Activity and Licensure of Massage Therapists, 2019 (Box 2)
  - An Act Relating to Labor and Labor Relations - Licensing (Rhode Island), 2019 (Box 2)
  - Arrest reports and related correspondence, 2016 - 2017 (Box 2)
  - Court case: Erotic Service Providers Legal, Education, and Research Project vs George Gascon; includes annotated case files and brief, 2015 (Box 2)
  - Court case: State of Rhode Island vs N. F.; includes criminal information, police narratives, and affidavits, 2013 (Box 2)
  - Criminal complaint forms, 2015 (Box 2)
  - House Bill 287 to decriminalize prostitution (New Hampshire); includes correspondence and news articles re: establishment of a committee to study issues related to changing prostitution laws, 2017 (Box 2)
  - House Bill 287 to decriminalize prostitution (New Hampshire); includes letters of support and news articles, 2017 (Box 2)
  - House Bill 5354 to create a special legislative commission to study the health and safety impact of revising commercial sexual activity laws (Rhode Island): written testimonies in support of the bill (1 of 2), 2019 (Box 2)
  - House Bill 5354 to create a special legislative commission to study the health and safety impact of revising commercial sexual activity laws (Rhode Island): written testimonies in support of the bill (2 of 2), 2019 (Box 2)
  - House Resolution to create a special legislative commission to study the health and safety impact of revising commercial sexual activity laws (Rhode Island), 2019 (Box 2)
  - Incident reports (Providence, Rhode Island), 2017 (Box 2)
  - Interview with Captain Michael Correia: typed transcript, 2015 (Box 2)